A Guide to the University of Connecticut, President's Office Records 1969.0004
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
University of Connecticut, President's Office Records
undated, 1881-
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1969.0004
333.25 Linear Feet
Records of the chief administrative officer of the University of Connecticut and its predecessor institutions. The records are subdivided by administration and identified and described by the name/tenure of the individual serving as president. In more recent years, the records are identified by date of transfer.
History
In April 1881, the Connecticut General Assembly established the Storrs Agricultural School after accepting a gift of 170 acres of land, several frame buildings, and money from Charles and Augustus Storrs. The School opened on 28 September 1881, with twelve students in the first class. Before the turn of the century there were two name changes (Storrs Agricultural College 1893, Connecticut Agricultural College 1899). In 1933, two years after the institution celebrated its fiftieth anniversary, it became Connecticut State College, a name more in keeping with its steady advances and broadened mission. Six years later, in 1939, the General Assembly designated the institution the University of Connecticut, an acknowledgment of the institution's developing importance to the State in graduate and professional education, research and public service.
The University of Connecticut is recognized as the state's flagship institution of higher learning. Since its establishment, the University has grown to include 13 Schools and Colleges at its main campus in Storrs, separate Schools of Law and Social Work in Hartford, four regional campuses throughout the state and Schools of Medicine and Dentistry at the UConn Health Center in Farmington.
UConn is a Land Grant and Sea Grant College and a Space Grant Consortium institution. The University spans 4,104 acres at its main campus and four regional campuses, and an additional 162 acres at the UConn Health Center in Farmington.
Designated a Carnegie Foundation Research University-Extensive, UConn has more than 70 focused research centers where faculty, graduate students and undergraduates explore everything from improving human health to enhancing public education and protecting the country's natural resources.
The office of the President was established in 1893 when the state of Connecticut established Storrs Agricultural College as Connecticut's land-grant institution of higher education. At that time the title of its chief administrative officer, Benjamin F. Koons, was changed from Principal of the former Storrs Agricultural School to President of the new college.
In the early days of Storrs and, from 1899, Connecticut Agricultural College, the President, aided by a few faculty committees, attended to virtually every detail of the administration of the college. At the time of the appointment of President Charles Lewis Beach in 1908, the Laws and By-laws of the College specified that the President, subject to the direction of the trustees, had "the immediate direction of all departments, and direction of all matters pertaining to the welfare of the college," including the appointment and dismissal of staff members and the designation of their duties. They also provided for his participation in all meetings of the Board of Trustees. As the College expanded its enrollment and its programs, an increasing amount of the President's responsibilities were delegated to other administrative officers. The 1921 catalog states that, under the supervision of the President, "the three branches of the administration are managed by the Faculty, the Director of the Experiment Station and the Director of the Extension Service." During President Beach's administration in 1921-1922, the College was divided into five academic divisions, each headed by a dean. The establishment of the office of the Dean of Women in 1928, Dean of Men in 1929, and Director of the Division of Resident Instruction, which later became Dean of the University, in 1931, were other important steps in the evolution of the Office of the President, as each more clearly defined the duties of the college's chief administrator. By the time Charles C. McCracken assumed the office in 1930, the President was concerned mainly with long-range policy-making, major campus issues, high-level appointments, and relations with the state and federal governments. The latter became more important during President Albert N. Jorgensen's tenure, when the various programs of the New Deal made many new kinds of federal funding available to land-grant colleges and universities.
When Connecticut State College became the University of Connecticut in 1939, the new laws and By-laws stated that, "the President of the University is the executive and administrative officer of the Board [of Trustees]. In this capacity he is responsible for the operations of the University and is given authority requisite to that end." This is the mandate under which President Jorgensen worked throughout his long service as President of the University. The President was also designated as "chairman of the University Senate and of the several schools and colleges." "The administrative reorganization authorized by President Jorgensen for the University in 1939 placed direct responsibility for the schools and colleges. President Jorgensen was thus able to devote all his energies chiefly to the fulfillment of his plans for the overall development of the University.
The names and terms of the Presidents of the University can be found here..
Arrangement
Series I: Solomon Mead (1881-1882) contains a copy of the course of study for 1882.
Series I: Solomon Mead
Series II: Benjamin Franklin Koons (1885-1898) contains photocopies of newspaper clippings, correspondence, articles concerning the school and a copy of a report.
Series II: Benjamin F. Koons
Series III: George Washington Flint (1900) contains newspaper clippings highlighting the controversies of Flint's tenure (1898-1901).
Series III: George W. Flint
Series IV: Rufus Whitaker Stimson (undated, 1899-1908) includes correspondence, publications, programs, an article written by Stimson and newspaper clippings.
Series IV: Rufus W. Stimson
Series V: Edwin Oscar Smith (1956-1958) served as acting President from April - September of 1908. The series includes one folder of correspondence between Smith and Mrs. Katharine Lusk regarding the dual job amendment.
Series VI: Charles Lewis Beach (undated, 1906-1929) contains correspondence, reports, studies and administrative records documenting the influence of Mr. Beach (1908-1928) while President of Connecticut Agricultural College.
Series VI: Charles L. Beach
Series VII: Charles Burt Gentry (undated, 1928-1969) consist of the general correspondence of the President of the College. It is the only extant collection of the papers of the president for this period. The correspondence is concerned with internal administrative matters, major policy issues at the college, with the college's relations with state and federal governments, and with other educational agencies and institutions. Also included is a collection of correspondence presented to Mr. Gentry on the event of his retirement from the University and a small folder of correspondence with the Gentry family pertaining to the naming of the Gentry Building.
Series VII: Charles B. Gentry
Series VIII: George Alan Works (undated, 1926-1930) The records consist of the general correspondence of the President of the College. The correspondence is concerned with internal administrative matters, major policy issues at the college, with the college's relations with state and federal governments, and with other educational agencies and institutions.
Series VIII: George A. Works
Series IX: Charles Chester McCracken (undated, 1926-1935) contains incoming and copies of outgoing correspondence documenting the activities of the administration and interests of the President of the institution. Materials pre-dating McCracken's tenure can be found in multiple folders, particularly in the 1930-1931 section, and have been noted in brackets in the folder listing.
Series IX: Charles C. McCracken
Series X: Albert Nels Jorgensen (1935-1962) includes general correspondence from 1935 to 1962. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically by topic within each academic year in one series. Because some of the Jorgensen papers were apparently inadvertently destroyed before they reached the University Archives, there is correspondence missing for the years 1942-1943, 1943-1944, 1945-1946, 1946-1947, and 1951-1952.
Series X: Albert N. Jorgensen
Series XI: Homer Daniels Babbidge, Jr. (1962-1972) documents his tenure as President of the University of Connecticut from 1962 through 1972. Included in the collection is correspondence, reports, minutes, memoranda, newspaper clippings, reports and publications, as well as materials documenting campus unrest and the files of his assistant, Wallace Moreland.
Series XI: Homer D. Babbidge, Jr.
Series XII: Edward Victor Gant (1969 July - October; 1972-1973; 1978-1979)
Series XIII: Glenn Walker Ferguson (undated, 1915-2005) documents his tenure as President of the University of Connecticut from 1973 through 1983. Included in the collection is correspondence, reports, minutes, memoranda, newspaper clippings, reports and publications, as well as materials documenting campus and state fiscal issues and the files of his assistant, Paul Capra and subsequent interim President Edward V. Gant. Also included are personal documents, correspondence, photographs, diaries, and emphemera from Ferguson's childhood through his careers as a diplomat, administrator of the Peace Corps/VISTA, academic administrator, and head of Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty and Lincoln Center.
Series XIII: Glenn W. Ferguson
Series XIV: John A. DiBiaggio (undated, 1952-1986) documents his tenure as President of the University of Connecticut from 1979 through 1985. Included in the collection is correspondence, reports, minutes, memoranda, newspaper clippings, reports and publications.
Series XIV: John A. DiBiaggio
Series XVI: Harry J. Hartley (undated, 1990-2000) collection contains the transcript of an interview between Dr. Hartley and Dr. Bruce Stave of the Center for Oral History and published materials documenting Dr. Hartley's activities while serving as the President of the University of Connecticut.
Series XVI: Harry J. Hartley
Series XVII: John T. Casteen (undated, 1981-1990) The records in this collection are the files of the President's office during John T. Casteen's administration from 1985-1990. The documents include correspondence, reports, financial and administrative records, as well as materials pertaining to his inauguration and plaques and mementos accumulated during his tenure as president.
Series XVI: John T. Casteen, III
Series XVIII: Philip E. Austin (1996-2007)
Series XVIII: Philip E. Austin
Series XIX: Michael J. Hogan ( 2007-2010 )
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The records are periodically transferred to Archives & Special Collections by the University President's Office for permanent retention.
College presidents; Notes; bylaws (administrative records); Resolutions (administrative records); Correspondence; Connecticut (state); Publications (documents); History; Education, Higher; Notebooks; Administrative records; Press releases; Photographs; Minutes (administrative records); Financial Records; Photocopies; University of Connecticut; University of Connecticut. President's Office
- Series I: Solomon Mead, 1882
  - Solomon Mead
- Series II: Benjamin F. Koons, 1885-1898
  - Benjamin F. Koons
- Series III: George W. Flint, 1900
  - George W. Flint
- Series IV: Rufus W. Stimson, undated, 1899-1908
  - Rufus W. Stimson
- Series V: Edwin O. Smith, 1956-1958
  - Edwin O. Smith
- Series VI: Charles L. Beach, undated, 1906-1929
  - Charles L. Beach
- Series VII: Charles B. Gentry, undated, 1928-1969
  - Charles B. Gentry
- Series VIII: George A. Works, undated, 1926-1930
  - George A. Works
- Series IX: Charles C. McCracken, undated, 1926-1935
  - Charles C. McCracken
- Series X: Albert Nels Jorgensen, 1935-1962
  - Albert N. Jorgensen
- Series XI: Homer D. Babbidge, Jr., undated, 1962-1972
  - Homer D. Babbidge, Jr.
- Series XIII: Glenn W. Ferguson, undated, 1973-1983
  - Glenn W. Ferguson
- Series XIV: John A. DiBiaggio, undated, 1952-1986
  - John DiBiaggio
- Series XVI: Harry J. Hartley, undated, 1990-2000
  - Harry J. Hartley
- Series XVII: John T. Casteen, III, undated, 1981-1990
  - John T. Casteen, III
- Series XVIII: Philip E. Austin, 1997-2007
  - Philip E. Austin
- Series XIX: Michael Hogan, 2007-2010
- Series XXI: 2009 Transfers
  - Unknown (Box 2009_1)
  - Unknown (Box 2009_2)
  - Unknown (Box 2009_3)
  - Unknown (Box 2009_5)
  - Unknown (Box 2009_4)
  - Unknown (Box 2009_10)
  - Unknown (Box 2009_11)
  - Unknown (Box 2009_12)
  - Unknown (Box 2009_13)
  - Unknown (Box 2009_14)
- Series XXII: 2012 Transfers
  - A-Z, 2008 (Box 2012_4)
  - Sweatshop Labor notebooks, 2006 (Box 2012_1)
  - Sweatship Labor files, 2006 (Box 2012_2)
  - Committee on Corporate Social Responsibility (formerly Sweatshop Labor), 2006-2009 (Box 2012_3)
- Series XXIII: 2013 Transfers, 2007-2010
  - A - N, 2009-2010 (Box 2013_1)
    Scope and Content Note
    BOX 2013-1 (Files from 2009-2010) Title Color Years A black 2009 A yellow 2010 ACE yellow 2009-10 Administrative Services, Dept of blue 2009 Affirmative Action Plan red 2009-10 Agriculture red 2009-10 Alcohol/Drugs red 2009 Alumni Assoc red 2009-10 Animal Care red 2010 Asian American Cultural Center red 2009 Asian American Studies red 2009 Athletics red 2009-10 Athletics-Basketball red 2009-10 Athletics-Big East red 2010 Athletics-Football red 2009-10 Athletics:NCAA red 2009-10 Athletics:NCAA Graduation Rates red 2009-10 Attorney red 2009-10 Attorney General blue 2009-10 Auditors blue 2009-10 Audit, Compliance & Ethics red 2009-10 Awards red 2009-10 B black 2009-10 B purple 2009 Biology red 2009 Board of Trustees red 2009-10 Branding red 2009 Budget-Biennial red 2010 Business, School of red 2009-10 C black 2009-10 C red 2009-10 C yellow 2009-10 C purple 2009 Campus Safety red 2009 CBIA black 2009 Centers and Institutes red 2009-10 Chemistry red 2009 Chief Financial Officer, VP and red 2009-10 Chief Operations Officer, VP and red 2009-10 Commencement red 2009-10 Communication Sciences, Dept of red 2009 Congressional/ Senate Inquiries green 2009-10 Congress: Washington Trips green 2009 CT Academy of Science and Engineering yellow 2009 Convocation red 2009-10 CT State University blue 2009-10 Correspondence red 2009-10 D red 2010 Dental Medicine red 2009-10 DHE blue 2009-10 DHE: ConnCAP blue 2009-10 DHE: ConnCAS blue 2009-10 Diversity & Equity, Office of red 2009 Dodd Archives & Research Center red 2009 Economics, Dept of red 2009 Education, Dept of green 2009-10 Education, Neag School of red 2009-10 Engineering, School of red 2009-10 English, Dept of red 2009-10 Enrollment Management red 2009-10 Environmental Policy/ Issues red 2009-10 Environmental Sciences & Engineering, Center for red 2009 Facilities red 2009 Finance, Revenue, Bonding blue 2009 Fine Arts red 2009-10 Fine Arts: Drama red 2009 Fraternities and Sororities red 2009 General Assembly blue 2009 Governmental Relations red 2009-10 Governor's Office blue 2009-10 H purple 2009-10 H yellow 2009-10 Hartford Hospital black 2010 History, Dept of red 2009-10 Homeland Security green 2009 Honors Program red 2009 Human Development & Family Studies red 2009 Human Resources red 2009-10 Human Rights Institute red 2009 I green 2009 I yellow 2009 IACUC red 2009-10 Information Technology, Dept of blue 2009 Information Technology Services red 2010 Institute for Materials Science red 2009 Institutional Advancement red 2009-10 International Programs red 2009-10 Jewish Matters (General) red 2009 L black 2010 Law School red 2009-10 Legislative Inquiries (alpha) blue 2009-10 Legislative Internship Program red 2009-10 Legislative Program Review blue 2009 Legislative Thank Yous blue 2009 Legislative--Misc. blue 2009-10 Liberal Arts & Sciences, College of red 2009 Library, Homer Babbidge red 2009-10 M black 2009-10 M purple 2009 Mansfield, Town of red 2009-10 Math Dept red 2009 Medicine, School of red 2009 Metro Hartford Alliance black 2009-10 Minority, Center for Academic Programs red 2009 Modern and Classical Languages red 2009 Molecular & Cell Biology red 2009 Museum of Art, Benton red 2009-10 Music, Dept of red 2009-10 N yellow 2009-10 NEASC yellow 2009-10 NEBHE yellow 2009 New England Council yellow 2009-10 NSF green 2009-10 Nursing, Scool of red 2009-10
  - O - Z, Archival files, 2009-2010 (Box 2013_2)
    O yellow 2009 OPM blue 2009-10 Outreach red 2009-10 P yellow 2009 Parking red 2009 Pharmacy red 2009 Physics red 2009 Political Science red 2010 Provost red 2009-10 Public Health, Dept of blue 2009 Public Safety, Dept of blue 2009 Public Safety, Division of red 2009-10 Purchasing red 2009-10 Regional Campuses red 2009-10 Research Issues red 2010 Scholarships--Misc red 2009-10 Senate red 2009 Social Work, School of red 2009 Sponsored Programs, Office of red 2009-10 Stem Cell red 2009-10 Student Affairs and Services red 2009-10 Student Affairs and Services: Food red 2009-10 Student Organizations: ConnPIRG red 2009 Student Organizations: Daily Campus red 2009 Student Organizations: SUBOG red 2009-10 Sympathy red 2009 T blue 2009 Tuition/Fees red 2009-10 U black 2009-10 University Relations red 2009 Urban League of Greater Hartford black 2009 USG red 2009 University Communications red 2009 Veterans Affairs blue 2010 W black 2010 W blue 2009 W yellow 2009
- 2014 Transfer, 1934-1970
  - Administrative Records, Correspondence, Financial Records, Notes, 1934-1970 (Box 2014-0149_1)
    President's Comm. on Equal Employment Opportunity, Student organizations, research corporation, refund of fees.
- 2015 Transfer, 1993-2009
  - Administrative records, Correspondence, 1993-2009 (Box 2015-0046_1)
    Administrative records including:
    UCONN Institution-Wide Administrative Assessment Final Report, February 1, 1999 Various BOT Committee meeting materials Correspondence Review of audit, June 25th, 2003 Audit subcommmitte meeting documents Committee on Instutional advancement Student Life committee documents UCONN Health Center review committee Health Affairs Committee meeting minutes September 30, 2000, March 30, 2001 Helath Affairs Committee, Fiscal year 1, Cost Improvement Opportunity Register